Today I want to talk about design,
اليوم أود الحديث عن التصميم،
but not design as we usually think about it.
لكن ليس التصميم كما قد نفكر فيه عادة.
I want to talk about what is happening now
أود الحديث عما يحدث الآن
in our scientific, biotechnological culture,
في ثقافتنا العلمية، والتكنوليجية الأحيائية،
where, for really the first time in history,
حيث، وللمرة الأولى في التاريخ،
we have the power to design bodies,
لدينا القدرة على تصميم أجسام،
to design animal bodies,
على تصميم أجسام حيوانات،
to design human bodies.
على تصميم أجسام بشرية.
In the history of our planet,
في تاريخ كوكبنا،
there have been three great waves of evolution.
قد حصلت ثلاث موجات تطور عظيمة.
The first wave of evolution
أول ثورة تطور
is what we think of as Darwinian evolution.
هي ما نعتقد على أنه التطور الدارويني.
So, as you all know,
هكذا، كما تعرفون جميعا،
species lived in particular ecological niches
عاشت الأصناف في أنماط حياتية معينة
and particular environments,
وأوساط معينة،
and the pressures of those environments
وضغوط هذه الأوساط
selected which changes,
حددت التغيرات،
through random mutation in species,
عن طريق طفرة عشوائية في أنواع،
were going to be preserved.
كان سيتم الحفاظ عليهم.
Then human beings stepped out
ثم خرج البشر
of the Darwinian flow of evolutionary history
من التيار الدارويني للتاريخ التطوري
and created the second great wave of evolution,
وأنشؤوا الموجة العظيمة الثانية للتطور،
which was we changed the environment
والتي كانت تغييرنا للبيئة
in which we evolved.
التي نشأنا فيها.
We altered our ecological niche
غيرنا نمطنا الحياتي
by creating civilization.
بإنشاء الحضارات.
And that has been the second great --
وذلك قد كان التيار العظيم الثاني --
couple 100,000 years, 150,000 years --
بضع مئات آلاف السنين، 150 ألف سنة --
flow of our evolution.
من التطور.
By changing our environment,
بتغيير البيئة.
we put new pressures
وضعنا ضغوطا جديدة
on our bodies to evolve.
على أجسادنا لتتطور.
Whether it was through settling down in agricultural communities,
سواء كانت عن طريق الإستقرار في المجتمعات الزراعية،
all the way through modern medicine,
وعلى طول الطريق من خلال الطب الحديث،
we have changed our own evolution.
غيرنا تطورنا الخاص.
Now we're entering a third great wave
ونحن الآن ندخل موجة ثالثة عظيمة
of evolutionary history,
من التاريخ التطوري.
which has been called many things:
والذي أطلقت عليه الكثير من الأسماء:
"intentional evolution,"
التطور المتعمد،
"evolution by design" --
التطوير عن طريق التصميم --
very different than intelligent design --
يختلف كثيرا عن التصميم الذكي --
whereby we are actually now
وبواسطته يمكننا الآن فعليا
intentionally designing and altering
أن نصمم ونغير عمدا
the physiological forms that inhabit our planet.
الأشكال الفسيولوجية التي تعيش على كوكبنا.
So I want to take you through a kind of whirlwind tour of that
وبالتالي أود أتطلع إلى أخذكم عن طريق نوع من الجولة الزوبعية لهذه الأشياء
and then at the end talk a little bit
وثم في النهاية نتحدث قليلا
about what some of the implications are for us
حول بعض آثار الحاصلة علينا
and for our species, as well as our cultures,
وعلى أنواعنا، فضلا عن ثقافتنا،
because of this change.
بسبب هذا التغيير.
Now we actually have been doing it for a long time.
الآن في الواقع قد استمرينا في القيام بهذا لوقت طويل.
We started selectively breeding animals
بدأنا بالاستيلاد الانتقائي للحيوانات
many, many thousands of years ago.
لآلاف سنين قد خلت.
And if you think of dogs for example,
وإن اتخذنا الكلاب كمثال،
dogs are now intentionally-designed creatures.
الكلاب اليوم مخلوقات مصممت قصدا.
There isn't a dog on this earth that's a natural creature.
ليس هناك كلب على هذه الأرض مخلوق طبيعيا.
Dogs are the result
الكلاب هي نتيجة
of selectively breeding traits that we like.
استيلاد انتقائي للصفات التي نود.
But we had to do it the hard way in the old days
لكن كان علينا القيام بذلك بالطريقة الصعبة قديما
by choosing offspring that looked a particular way
باختيار نسل بشكل معين
and then breeding them.
ثم استيلادهم.
We don't have to do it that way anymore.
لم يعد لزاما علينا أن نقوم بذلك بعد الآن.
This is a beefalo.
هذا بيقر.
A beefalo is a buffalo-cattle hybrid.
بيقر هو هجين بيسون وبقر.
And they are now making them,
ويتم الآن إنتاجهم،
and someday, perhaps pretty soon,
ويوما ما، ربما قريبا،
you will have beefalo patties
ستتوفرون على فطائر البيقر
in your local supermarket.
في الأسواق الممتازة المحلية.
This is a geep,
هذا مروف.
a goat-sheep hybrid.
هجين ماعز، وخروف.
The scientists that made this cute little creature
العلماء الذين أنشؤوا هذا المخلوق الصغير الفاتن
ended up slaughtering it and eating it afterwards.
انتهوا بذبحه وأكله فيما بعد.
I think they said it tasted like chicken.
أعتقد أنهم قالوا بأن له مذاق يشبه الدجاج.
This is a cama.
هذا جاما.
A cama is a camel-llama hybrid,
والجاما هي هجين الجمل واللاما،
created to try to get the hardiness of a camel
تم انشاؤها للحصول على شجاعة الجمل
with some of the personality traits
مع بعض الصفات الشخصية
of a llama.
للاما.
And they are now using these in certain cultures.
ويتم الآن استخدامها في بعض الحضارات.
Then there's the liger.
ثم ها هو الأسد الببري.
This is the largest cat in the world --
هذا أكبر قط في العالم --
the lion-tiger hybrid.
هجين الأسد والنمر.
It's bigger than a tiger.
هو أضخم من النمر.
And in the case of the liger,
وفي حالة الأسد الببري،
there actually have been one or two that have been seen in the wild.
فقد تم مشاهدة واحد أو اثنان منها في البر.
But these were created by scientists
لكن هذه تم إنشاؤها من طرف العلماء
using both selective breeding and genetic technology.
باستخدام الاستيلاد الانتقائي مع التكنولوجيا الجينية.
And then finally, everybody's favorite,
وثم أخيرا، والمفضل عند الجميع،
the zorse.
الزران. (هجين ذكر حمار الزرد وأنثى الحصان).
None of this is Photoshopped. These are real creatures.
لا شيء من هذا تم تعديله بالفوتوشوب؛ هذه مخلوقات حقيقية.
And so one of the things we've been doing
وبالتالي أحد الأشياء التي نقوم بها
is using genetic enhancement,
هي استخدام التحسينات الجينية،
or genetic manipulation,
أو التلاعب الجيني،
of normal selective breeding
لاستيلاد انتقائي عادي
pushed a little bit through genetics.
مدفوع قليلا عن طريق علم الوراثة.
And if that were all this was about,
وإن كان ذلك كل ما يتعلق بالأمر،
then it would be an interesting thing.
لكان الأمر مثيرا للإهتمام.
But something much, much more powerful
لكن هناك أمر في غاية القوة
is happening now.
يحدث الآن.
These are normal mammalian cells
هذه خلايا ثديات عادية
genetically engineered with a bioluminescent gene
تمت هندستها وراثيا بجينات ضيائية حيوية
taken out of deep-sea jellyfish.
مأخوذة من السمك الهلامي من عمق المحيط.
We all know that some deep-sea creatures glow.
كلنا يعلم أن بعض مخلوقات الأعماق تتوهج.
Well, they've now taken that gene, that bioluminescent gene,
حسنا، لقد أخذوا تلك الجينة، تلك المورثة الضيائية الحيوية،
and put it into mammal cells.
ووضعوها في خلايا ثدية.
These are normal cells.
هذه خلايا عادية.
And what you see here
وما ترونه هنا
is these cells glowing in the dark
هو هذه الخلايا وهي تتوهج في الظلام
under certain wavelengths of light.
تحت أطوال موجات ضوئية محددة.
Once they could do that with cells, they could do it with organisms.
وبمجرد أن أمكنهم القيام بذلك على الخلايا، أمكنهم القيام به على الكائنات الحية.
So they did it with mouse pups,
وبالتالي أجروا ذلك على الفئران والجراء
kittens.
والقطط.
And by the way, the reason the kittens here are orange and these are green
وبالمناسبة، فإن سبب كون القطط برتقالية وهذه خضراء
is because that's a bioluminescent gene from coral,
هو راجع لأن تلك الجينات الضيائية الحيوية مأخوذة من المرجان،
while this is from jellyfish.
في حين أخذت هذه من السمك الهلامي.
They did it with pigs.
أجروا ذلك على الخنازير،
They did it with puppies.
وعلى الجراء،
And, in fact,
و، في الواقع،
they did it with monkeys.
قاموا بذلك على السعادين كذلك.
And if you can do it with monkeys --
وإن أمكنكم القيام بذلك على السعادين --
though the great leap in trying to genetically manipulate
مع أن الوثبة العظيمة في محاولة التلاعب الجيني
is actually between monkeys and apes --
هي في الواقع بين السعادين والقرود --
if they can do it in monkeys,
إن أمكنهم القيام بذلك على السعادين،
they can probably figure out how to do it in apes,
يمكنهم ربما إيجاد طريقة لتطبيقه على القرود،
which means they can do it in human beings.
وبالتالي يمكنهم القيام بذلك على البشر.
In other words, it is theoretically possible
بعبارة أخرى، من الممكن نظريا
that before too long we will be biotechnologically capable
أنه قبل فترة طويلة جدا سنكون قادرين من خلال التكنولوجيا الحيوية
of creating human beings
على إنشاء بشر
that glow in the dark.
يتوهجون في الظلام.
Be easier to find us at night.
ليكون سهلا إيجادنا ليلا.
And in fact, right now in many states,
وفي الحقيقة، حاليا وفي العديد من الولايات،
you can go out and you can buy bioluminescent pets.
يمكنك الخروج لشراء حيوانات أليفة ضيائية حيوية.
These are zebra fish. They're normally black and silver.
هناك السمك الصغير المخطط. في العادة تكون سوداء وفضية.
These are zebra fish that have been genetically engineered
هذا السمك الصغير المخطط قد تمت هندسته وراثيا.
to be yellow, green, red,
ليكون أصفر وأخضر وأحمر،
and they are actually available now in certain states.
وهي بالفعل متوفرة في بعض الولايات.
Other states have banned them.
الولايات الأخرى منعتها.
Nobody knows what to do with these kinds of creatures.
لا أحد يعرف كيف نتعامل مع هذا النوع من المخلوقات.
There is no area of the government -- not the EPA or the FDA --
ليست هناك أي جهة حكومية -- ليس ال EPA أو FDA --
that controls genetically-engineered pets.
تتحكم في الحيوانات الأليفة المهندسة وراثيا.
And so some states have decided to allow them,
وبالتالي بعض الولايات قررت السماح بها،
some states have decided to ban them.
وبعضها قرر منعها.
Some of you may have read
بعضكم قد يكون قرأ
about the FDA's consideration right now
حول دراسة الFDA حاليا
of genetically-engineered salmon.
للسلمون المهندس وراثيا.
The salmon on top
السلمون في الأعلى
is a genetically engineered Chinook salmon,
هو سلمون شينوك تمت هندسته وراثيا،
using a gene from these salmon
باستخدام جينة من هذا السلمون
and from one other fish that we eat,
ومن سمك آخر نأكله
to make it grow much faster
لجعله ينمو بشكل أسرع
using a lot less feed.
باستخدام طعام أقل.
And right now the FDA is trying to make a final decision
وحاليا تحاول ال FDA التوصل إلى قرار نهائي
on whether, pretty soon, you could be eating this fish --
حول ما إذا، في القريب العاجل، يمكنك تناول هذا السمك --
it'll be sold in the stores.
سيباع في المحلات.
And before you get too worried about it,
وقبل أن تقلق بخصوص ذلك،
here in the United States,
هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
the majority of food you buy in the supermarket
أغلب الطعام الذي تشتريه من الأسواق الممتازة
already has genetically-modified components to it.
يحتوي مسبقا على مكونات معدلة وراثيا فيه.
So even as we worry about it,
ولهذا حتى ونحن قلقون بخصوصها،
we have allowed it to go on in this country -- much different in Europe --
قد سمحنا لها بالدخول إلى هذه الدولة -- مع اختلاف كبير في أوروبا --
without any regulation,
بدون أية قواعد،
and even without any identification on the package.
وحتى بدون أي كشف محدد على الرزمة.
These are all the first cloned animals
هذه هي أوائل الحيوانات المستنتسخة
of their type.
من نوعها.
So in the lower right here,
إذن في أسفل اليمين هنا،
you have Dolly, the first cloned sheep --
لدينا دولي، أول نعجة مستنسخة --
now happily stuffed in a museum in Edinburgh;
الآن لحسن الحظ محشورة في متحف في ادنبره؛
Ralph the rat, the first cloned rat;
رالف الجرذ، أول جرذ مستنسخ؛
CC the cat, for cloned cat;
سيسي القط، في القطط المستنسخة؛
Snuppy, the first cloned dog --
سنوبي، أول كلب مستنستخ
Snuppy for Seoul National University puppy --
سنوبي مشتقة من: جرو الجامعة الوطنية في سيول (SNU-Puppy) --
created in South Korea
تم تكوينه في كوريا الجنوبية
by the very same man that some of you may remember
بواسطة نفس الرجل الذي قد يتذكره بعضكم
had to end up resigning in disgrace
الذي قدم استقالته في عار
because he claimed he had cloned a human embryo, which he had not.
لأنه ادعى أنه قد استنسخ جنينا بشريا، والذي لم يفعله.
He actually was the first person
وهو في الواقع أول شخص
to clone a dog, which is a very difficult thing to do,
يستنسخ كلبا، وهو أمر غاية في الصعوبة،
because dog genomes are very plastic.
لأن مورثات الكلب ذات مرونة عالية.
This is Prometea, the first cloned horse.
هذا بروميتيا، أول حصان مستنسخ.
It's a Haflinger horse cloned in Italy,
إنه حصان من سلالة هيفلينغر مستنسخ في إيطاليا،
a real "gold ring" of cloning,
خاتم ذهبي حقيقي للاستنساخ،
because there are many horses that win important races
لأن هناك الكثير من الأحصنة التي تفوز بسباقات مهمة
who are geldings.
وتكون مخصية.
In other words, the equipment to put them out to stud
بعبارة أخرى، المعدات اللازمة للاستيلاد
has been removed.
تمت إزالتها.
But if you can clone that horse,
لكن إن أمكننا استنساخ هذا الحصان،
you can have both the advantage of having a gelding run in the race
سيكون لدينا ميزة التوفر على مخصي يجري في السباق
and his identical genetic duplicate
ونسخته المتطابقة جينيا
can then be put out to stud.
يمكن تركها للاستيلاد.
These were the first cloned calves,
هذه أولى العجول المستنسخة،
the first cloned grey wolves,
أولى الذئاب الرمادية المستنسخة.
and then, finally,
وثم في الختام،
the first cloned piglets:
أولى الخنازير المستنسخة:
Alexis, Chista, Carrel, Janie and Dotcom.
أليكسيس وتشيستا وكارول وجيني ودوتكوم.
(Laughter)
(ضحكات)
In addition, we've started to use cloning technology
إضافة إلى ذلك، بدأنا نستخدم تكنولوجيا الإستنساخ
to try to save endangered species.
لمحاولة إنقاذ الأصناف المهددة بالإنقراض.
This is the use of animals now
هذا الإستخدام الحالي للحيوانات
to create drugs and other things in their bodies
تكوين العقاقير وأشياء أخرى في أجسامها
that we want to create.
التي نريد تكوينها.
So with antithrombin in that goat --
وبالتالي مع تواجد مضاد الثرومبين في تلك الماعز --
that goat has been genetically modified
تلك الماعز تم تعديلها وراثيا
so that the molecules of its milk
بحيث أن جزيئات حليبها
actually include the molecule of antithrombin
تضم بالفعل جزيئات مضاد الثرومبين
that GTC Genetics wants to create.
الذي تريد GTC للوراثيات تكوينه.
And then in addition, transgenic pigs, knockout pigs,
ثم وكذلك، الخنازير بالجينات المتصلة وراثيا، والخنازير بالجينات المعطلة،
from the National Institute of Animal Science in South Korea,
من المعهد الوطني لعلوم الحيوان في كوريا الجنوبية،
are pigs that they are going to use, in fact,
وهي خنازير التي سيقومون باستخدامها، في الواقع،
to try to create all kinds of drugs
لمحاولة إنشاء كل أنواع العقاقير
and other industrial types of chemicals
وأنواع صناعية أخرى من الكيماويات
that they want the blood and the milk
والتي يريدون من دم وحليب
of these animals
هذه الحيوانات
to produce for them,
أن ينتجها لهم،
instead of producing them in an industrial way.
بدل إنتاجها بطريقة صناعية.
These are two creatures
هذان مخلوقان
that were created
تم تكوينهما
in order to save endangered species.
من أجل حماية الأصناف المهددة بالإنقراض.
The guar
الغار
is an endangered Southeast Asian ungulate.
هو أحد ذوات الحوافر المهددة بالإنقراض في جنوب شرق آسيا.
A somatic cell, a body cell,
خلية جسدية، خلية جسمية،
was taken from its body,
تم أخذها من جسده،
gestated in the ovum of a cow,
وتحميلها في بويضة بقرة،
and then that cow gave birth to a guar.
ثم أنجبت البقرة غارا.
Same thing happened with the mouflon,
نفس الأمر وقع مع الموفلون،
where it's an endangered species of sheep.
حيث انها من الأنواع المهددة بالانقراض من الأغنام.
It was gestated in a regular sheep body,
تم تحميلها في جسد خروف عادي،
which actually raises an interesting biological problem.
والذي يثير في الواقع مشكلة حيوية مثيرة للاهتمام.
We have two kinds of DNA in our bodies.
نتوفر في أجسادنا على نوعين من الحمض النووي.
We have our nucleic DNA
لدينا الحمض النووي النووي
that everybody thinks of as our DNA,
والذي يعتبره الجميع الحمض النووي
but we also have DNA in our mitochondria,
لكن لدينا كذلك حمض نووي في الميتوكوندريا لدينا،
which are the energy packets of the cell.
والتي هي الجيوب الطاقية للخلية.
That DNA is passed down through our mothers.
هذا الحمض النووي ورثناه عن طريق أمهاتنا.
So really, what you end up having here
لذلك فعليا، ما نحصل عليه هنا
is not a guar and not a mouflon,
هو ليس غار ولا موفلون،
but a guar
لكنه غار
with cow mitochondria,
بميتوكوندريا بقرية،
and therefore cow mitochondrial DNA,
وبالتالي حمض نووي بقري في الميتوكوندريا،
and a mouflon with another species of sheep's
وحمض موفلون وأنواع أخرى من الغنم
mitochondrial DNA.
نووي في المتيوكوندريا.
These are really hybrids, not pure animals.
هاته بالفعل هجينات وليس حيوانات نقية.
And it raises the question of how we're going to define animal species
والسؤال الذي يثار هو كيف يمكننا تصنيف الأنواع الحيوانية
in the age of biotechnology --
في عصر التكنولوجيا الحيوية --
a question that we're not really sure yet
وهو سؤال لسنا فعلا متأكدين بعد حول
how to solve.
كيفية حله.
This lovely creature
هذا المخلوق الجميل
is an Asian cockroach.
هو صرصور آسيوي.
And what they've done here
وما قاموا به هنا
is they've put electrodes in its ganglia and its brain
هو أنهم وضعوا أقطابا كهربائية في دماغها وعقدها العصبي
and then a transmitter on top,
ثم باعث في الأعلى،
and it's on a big computer tracking ball.
وهي على كرة كبيرة يتم تتبعها بالكمبيوتر.
And now, using a joystick,
والآن، باستخدام عصا تحكم،
they can send this creature
يمكنهم إرسال هذا المخلوق
around the lab
حول المختبر
and control whether it goes left or right,
والتحكم في توجهه إلى اليمين أو اليسار،
forwards or backwards.
إلى الأمام أو إلى الخلف.
They've created a kind of insect bot,
قد كونوا نوعا من الروباتات الحشرية.
or bugbot.
أو الروبوتات البقية.
It gets worse than that -- or perhaps better than that.
تزداد الأمور سوء -- أو ربما تتحسن.
This actually is one of DARPA's very important --
هذا في الواقع أحد أهم مشاريع DARPA --
DARPA is the Defense Research Agency --
DARPA هي وكالة الدفاع للبحوث --
one of their projects.
أحد مشاريعهم.
These goliath beetles
خنافس جالوت هذه
are wired in their wings.
مربوطة بأسلاك في أجنحتها.
They have a computer chip strapped to their backs,
لديها رقاقة كمبيوتر مربوطة في ظهورها،
and they can fly these creatures around the lab.
ويمكنهم التحكم في طيران هاته المخلوقات حول المختبر.
They can make them go left, right. They can make them take off.
بإمكانهم جعلها تذهب يسارا ويمينا. يمكنهم جعلها تقلع.
They can't actually make them land.
لا يمكنهم في الواقع جعلها تهبط.
They put them about one inch above the ground,
يقومون فقط بموضعتها فوق السطح بإنش واحد،
and then they shut everything off and they go pfft.
ثم يقومون بإيقاف تشغيل كل شيء ثم يدعونها تسقط.
But it's the closest they can get to a landing.
لكنها أقرب ما وصلوا إليه كهبوط.
And in fact, this technology has gotten so developed
وفي الواقع، هذه التكنولوجيا قد تم تطويرها
that this creature --
إلى درجة أن هذا المخلوق --
this is a moth --
هذه عثة.
this is the moth in its pupa stage,
هذه عثة في مرحلة العذرية،
and that's when they put the wires in
ذلك حين يضعون الأسلاك فيها
and they put in the computer technology,
ثم يضعون تكنولوجيا الكمبيوتر.
so that when the moth actually emerges as a moth,
بحيث أنه حين تخرج العثة كعثة،
it is already prewired.
تكون موصولة بالأسلاك مسبقا.
The wires are already in its body,
الأسلاك موجودة مسبقا في جسدها،
and they can just hook it up to their technology,
ويمكنهم فقط ربطها بالتكنولوجيا لديهم،
and now they've got these bugbots
لتكون لديهم هذه الروبوتات الحشرية
that they can send out for surveillance.
ويمكنهم إرسالها من أجل المراقبة.
They can put little cameras on them
يمكنهم وضع كاميرات صغيرة عليها
and perhaps someday deliver
وربما يوما ما تسليم
other kinds of ordinance
أنواع أخرى من المتفجرات
to warzones.
لمناطق الحرب.
It's not just insects.
ليست مجرد حشرات.
This is the ratbot, or the robo-rat
هذا الجرذ الروبوت، أو الروبو-جرذ
by Sanjiv Talwar at SUNY Downstate.
من طرف سانجيف تالوار في جامعة ولاية نيويورك داونستيت.
Again, it's got technology --
مجددا، يحتوي على التكنولوجيا،
it's got electrodes going into its left and right hemispheres;
لده أقطاب كهربائية متصلة بنصفي دماغه الأيمن والأيسر،
it's got a camera on top of its head.
لديه كاميرا فوق رأسه.
The scientists can make this creature
يمكن للعلماء جعل هذا المخلوق
go left, right.
يذهب يمينا ويسارا.
They have it running through mazes, controlling where it's going.
يجعلونه يجري في متاهات متحكمين في وجهته.
They've now created an organic robot.
وقد كونوا الآن روبوتا عضويا.
The graduate students
طلاب الدراسات العليا
in Sanjiv Talwar's lab
في مختبر سانجيف تالوار
said, "Is this ethical?
قالوا: "هل هذا أخلاقي؟
We've taken away the autonomy of this animal."
لقد قمنا بأخذ استقلالية هذا الحيوان."
I'll get back to that in a minute.
سأعود إلى هذا خلال دقيقة.
There's also been work done with monkeys.
وهناك كذلك أعمال أجريت على السعادين.
This is Miguel Nicolelis of Duke.
هذا ميغيل نيكوليليس من ديوك.
He took owl monkeys,
أخذ سعدان البومة،
wired them up
وربطهم بالأسلاك
so that a computer watched their brains while they moved,
بحيث يتمكن كمبيوتر من تتبع أدمغتهم وهم يتحركون،
especially looking at the movement of their right arm.
وبالخصوص النظر إلى حركة الذراع الأيمن.
The computer learned what the monkey brain did
الكمبيوتر تعلم ما قام به دماغ السعادين
to move its arm in various ways.
لتحريك الذراع بطرق مختلفة.
They then hooked it up to a prosthetic arm,
ثم ربطوه بذراع اصطناعية،
which you see here in the picture,
والتي ترونها هنا في الصورة،
put the arm in another room.
وضعوا الذراع في غرفة أخرى.
Pretty soon, the computer learned, by reading the monkey's brainwaves,
وبعد مدة وجيزة، تعلم الكمبيوتر عن طريق قراءة الأمواج الدماغية للسعادين،
to make that arm in the other room
أن يجعل الذراع الموجودة في الغرفة الأخرى
do whatever the monkey's arm did.
تقوم بكل ما تقوم به ذراع السعدان.
Then he put a video monitor
ثم وضع شاشة فيديو
in the monkey's cage
في قفص السعادين
that showed the monkey this prosthetic arm,
تري السعدان هاته اليد الإصطناعية،
and the monkey got fascinated.
فافتتن بها السعدان،
The monkey recognized that whatever she did with her arm,
أدرك السعدان أن كل ما فعلته بذراعها،
this prosthetic arm would do.
تقوم به الذراع الإصطناعية كذلك.
And eventually she was moving it and moving it,
وفي نهاية المطاف كانت تحركها مرارا وتكرارا،
and eventually stopped moving her right arm
ثم أخيرا توقفت عن تحريك ذراعها الأيمن
and, staring at the screen,
وبدأت وبالتحديق في الشاشة،
could move the prosthetic arm in the other room
استطاعت تحريك الذراع الإصطناعية في الغرفة الأخرى
only with her brainwaves --
فقط عن طريق أمواجها الدماغية --
which means that monkey
أي أن تلك السعدان
became the first primate in the history of the world
صارت أول رئيسية في تاريخ العالم
to have three independent functional arms.
تتوفر على ثلاثة أذرع عاملة مستقلة.
And it's not just technology
وليست فقط التكنولوجيا
that we're putting into animals.
هي ما نضعه في الحيوانات.
This is Thomas DeMarse at the University of Florida.
هذا هو توماس ديمارس في جامعة ولاية فلوريدا.
He took 20,000 and then 60,000
أخذ 20,000 ثم 60,000
disaggregated rat neurons --
خلايا عصبية مصنفة من الجرذ --
so these are just individual neurons from rats --
إذن هذه مجرد خلايا عصبية منفردة من الجرذان --
put them on a chip.
ضعها في رقاقة.
They self-aggregated into a network,
تتجمع ذاتيا في شبكة،
became an integrated chip.
وتصير رقاقة متكاملة.
And he used that
واستخدم ذلك
as the IT piece
كقطعة معلوماتية
of a mechanism which ran a flight simulator.
لآلية تشغل محاكي الطيران.
So now we have organic computer chips
وبالتالي لدينا الآن رقاقات كمبيوتر عضوية
made out of living, self-aggregating neurons.
مصنوعة من خلايا عصبية حية ذاتية التجميع.
Finally, Mussa-Ivaldi of Northwestern
وأخيرا، موسى-لفالدي من نورث وسترن
took a completely intact,
أخذ دماغا سليما تماما
independent lamprey eel brain.
ومستقلا لجِلكي.
This is a brain from a lamprey eel.
هذا دماغ جِلكي.
It is living --
دماغ حي،
fully-intact brain in a nutrient medium
وسليم تماما في وسط مغذي
with these electrodes going off to the sides,
بهاته الأقطاب خارجة إلى الجوانب،
attached photosensitive sensors to the brain,
وأجهزة استشعار صوري متصلة بالدماغ،
put it into a cart --
وضع في عربة --
here's the cart, the brain is sitting there in the middle --
ها هي العربة، الدماغ موجود هناك في الوسط --
and using this brain as the sole processor for this cart,
وباستخدام هذا الدماغ كمعالج وحيد لهذه العربة،
when you turn on a light and shine it at the cart,
حين تشعل ضوء وتلقي به على العربة،
the cart moves toward the light;
تتحرك العربة في اتجاه الضوء؛
when you turn it off, it moves away.
حين تطفئه، تتحرك بعيدا.
It's photophilic.
إنها محبة للضوء.
So now we have a complete
وبالتالي لدينا الآن دماغ كامل
living lamprey eel brain.
لجلكي حي.
Is it thinking lamprey eel thoughts,
هل يفكر في أفكار جلكي،
sitting there in its nutrient medium?
وهو جالس هناك في وسطه المغذي؟
I don't know,
لا أعرف،
but in fact it is a fully living brain
لكن في الواقع هو دماغ كامل حي
that we have managed to keep alive
استطعنا الإبقاء عليه حيا
to do our bidding.
للقيام بمزايداتنا.
So, we are now at the stage
وهكذا، نحن الآن في مرحلة
where we are creating creatures
نستطيع فيها إنشاء مخلوقات
for our own purposes.
تخدم أهدافنا الخاصة.
This is a mouse created by Charles Vacanti
هذا فأر انشأه تشارلز فاكانتي
of the University of Massachusetts.
من جامعة ماساتشوستس.
He altered this mouse
غير هذا الفأر
so that it was genetically engineered
بحيث جعله مهندسا وراثيا
to have skin that was less immunoreactive to human skin,
ليتوفر على جلد أقل مناعية للجلد البشري،
put a polymer scaffolding of an ear under it
وضع سقالات بوليمير على شكل أذن تحته
and created an ear that could then be taken off the mouse
وأنشأ أذنا يمكن أخذها من الفأر
and transplanted onto a human being.
وزرعها في الإنسان.
Genetic engineering
الهندسة الوراثية
coupled with polymer physiotechnology
مع تكنولوجيا البوليمير الطبية
coupled with xenotransplantation.
مع زراعة الأعضاء.
This is where we are in this process.
هذا ما وصلنا إليه في هاته السيرورة.
Finally, not that long ago,
أخيرا، قبل مدة ليست بالطويلة،
Craig Venter created the first artificial cell,
أنشأ كريغ فينتر أول خلية صناعية،
where he took a cell, took a DNA synthesizer,
حيث أخذ خلية، ومازج حمض نووي،
which is a machine,
والذي هو آلة،
created an artificial genome,
وأنشأ مورثة صناعية،
put it in a different cell --
وضعها في خلية مختلفة --
the genome was not of the cell he put it in --
المورثة لم تكن من المورثة التي وضعت فيها --
and that cell then reproduced
ثم استنسخت تلك الخلية
as the other cell.
كالخلية الأخرى.
In other words,
بعبارة أخرى،
that was the first creature in the history of the world
ذلك كان أول مخلوق في تاريخ العالم
that had a computer as its parent --
يتوفر على كمبيوتر كأصل --
it did not have an organic parent.
لم يتوفر على أصل عضوي.
And so, asks The Economist:
وبالتالي، تسأل مجلة الإيكونوميست:
"The first artificial organism and its consequences."
"أول كائن مصطنع وعواقبه."
So you may have thought
إذن قد تكونوا قد فكرتم
that the creation of life
ان إنشاء حياة
was going to happen in something that looked like that.
سيحدث في مكان يبدو كهذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحكات)
But in fact, that's not what Frankenstein's lab looks like.
لكن في الواقع، ليس هكذا يبدو مختبر فرنكشتاين.
This is what Frankenstein's lab looks like.
هكذا يبدو مختبر فرنكشتاين.
This is a DNA synthesizer,
هذا مازج الحمض النووي،
and here at the bottom
وهناك في الأسفل
are just bottles of A, T, C and G --
مجرد قناني من A و T وC وG --
the four chemicals
الأنواع الكيميائية الأربعة
that make up our DNA chain.
التي تكون سلسلة حمضنا النووي.
And so, we need to ask ourselves some questions.
وبالتالي، يجب علينا أن نطرح على أنفسنا بعض الأسئلة.
For the first time in the history of this planet,
لأول مرة في تاريخ الكوكب،
we are able to directly design organisms.
نحن قادرون على تصميم كائنات مباشرة.
We can manipulate the plasmas of life
نستطيع التلاعب ببلازما الحياة
with unprecedented power,
بقوة غير مسبوقة.
and it confers on us a responsibility.
وذلك يضع على عاتقنا مسؤولية.
Is everything okay?
هل كل شيء مباح؟
Is it okay to manipulate and create
هل من المباح التلاعب ب وإنشاء
whatever creatures we want?
أي مخلوقات نريد؟
Do we have free reign
هل لدينا سيادة مجانية
to design animals?
لتصميم الحيوانات؟
Do we get to go someday to Pets 'R' Us
هل من المسموح لنا أن نذهب يوما ما ل Pets "R" Us
and say, "Look, I want a dog.
ونقول، "انظر، أريد كلبا.
I'd like it to have the head of a Dachshund,
وأريده أن يتوفر على رأس كلب ألماني،
the body of a retriever,
وجسد كلب مكتشف،
maybe some pink fur,
وربما بعض الفراء الوردي،
and let's make it glow in the dark"?
ولنجعله يتوهج في الظلام."
Does industry get to create creatures
هل من المسموح للصناعة بإنشاء كائنات
who, in their milk, in their blood, and in their saliva
في حليبها، ودمها ولعابها
and other bodily fluids,
وسوئل أخرى من أجسادها،
create the drugs and industrial molecules we want
تنتج العقاقير والجزيئات الإصطناعية التي نريد
and then warehouse them
وثم تخزينها
as organic manufacturing machines?
كآلات تصنيع عضوية؟
Do we get to create organic robots,
هل من المسموح لنا أن ننشئ روبوتات عضوية،
where we remove the autonomy from these animals
بحيث نزيل استقلالية هاته الحيوانات
and turn them just into our playthings?
ونحولها إلى أشياء نلعب بها؟
And then the final step of this,
وأخيرا الخطوة الأخيرة في الأمر،
once we perfect these technologies in animals
ما إن نتقن هاته التكنولوجيات على الحيوانات
and we start using them in human beings,
ونبدأ في استعمالها على البشر،
what are the ethical guidelines
ما هي القواعد الأخلاقية
that we will use then?
التي سنستخدم آنذاك؟
It's already happening. It's not science fiction.
إنه أمر حاصل بالفعل؛ ليس خيالا علميا.
We are not only already using these things in animals,
لسنا فقط بالفعل نستخدم هذه الأشياء على الحيوانات،
some of them we're already beginning to use
بعضها قد بدأنا نستخدمها
on our own bodies.
في أجسادنا.
We are now taking control of our own evolution.
نحن الآن نتحكم في ثورتنا الخاصة.
We are directly designing
نصمم بشكل مباشر
the future of the species of this planet.
مستقبل الأنواع في هذا الكوكب.
It confers upon us an enormous responsibility
وذلك يضع على عاتقنا مسؤولية
that is not just the responsibility
تلك ليست فقط مسؤولية
of the scientists and the ethicists
العلماء والأخلاقيين
who are thinking about it and writing about it now.
الذين يفكرون في الأمر ويكتبون عنه الآن.
It is the responsibility of everybody
إنها مسؤولية الجميع
because it will determine what kind of planet and what kind of bodies
لأنها ستحدد نوع الكوكب والأجساد
we will have in the future.
التي سنتوفر عليها في المستقبل.
Thanks.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)